[Music]
a
hello good day good evening everybody I
hope you're all doing very well and
welcome to the askit show the first
episode of the Year 2024 I hope you're
all doing very well
uh it's been a while since we did these
episodes so yeah we are back on the
track now and we're going to do a lot
more these years uh this year yeah so
looking forward to that so uh I hope
you're all doing very well and let me
see who all is there on the live stream
let me see lots of comments let's see
who all is there uh I can see shash
shank Neo Neo SG VI sing green ray
Shivam tiari Maximus Decimus Gotham
pendal Shivam Singh Think Tank kitar
Sony midnight
stalker Rubin there mwami aay Neo jnit
Singh Sur Neo abishek poia Sam bade goam
vun Arpita pan ADI Ander nagri gamer
Vladimir
zelinski manav vendra KL BP vinit
Krishna VI Anand RI geopolitical dub man
Sanjay Kumar Singh vijes mukun Jack Tas
Nishant Vishnu prit
Raj Anand Neo Arpita animy STS threat
rapper rajat Duhan rajat Singh raat ruaj
Krishna suant tanai Ravi sarak GK Amisha
Shashank Rahul tagat and so many so many
other people trupti Patel Janel Joel Jo
Nishant
uh Amit Dr Amit arbind takur Pavan Kumar
Singh B prit again AES and and so many
other people ver subrahmanyam J Shankar
Anish Prashant DOI and everybody else I
can see some more Puja vs Captain Kepler
Sid D and so on so I will not be able to
greet you all individually because
otherwise it'll take all night but thank
you so much for being on the live stream
it's great to be back on the live stream
so in this live stream I'm going to uh
I'm going to take questions as always
I'm going to take questions from the
live chat mostly but I've also taken
some questions that have people have
asked in the comments so a few of those
must but mostly from the live stream so
that's what we will do and uh you can
start with the questions or maybe I can
take one take a question from um um um
um that I had taken from the comments so
let's do that and that brings us to the
announcement so here's the question
uh lots of people I get this question
all the time U is there any course to
study geopolitics in India how to how
can we study geopolitics are there some
books to guide us or any method to
observing what's actually happening
behind the scenes how to analyze
International relationships without any
ideological influence of other
people how to get a proper knowledge of
geopolitics can we just
uh uh yeah no proper answer no can we
just read a bunch of newspapers so you
cannot do that and there are no
textbooks on geopolitics and there is no
such thing so that's why I have gone
ahead and created a course on
geopolitics yes it is time to announce
the course and it's going to be the best
course of its kind on geopolitics it's
called geopolitics from first principal
so let me show you what the course looks
like this is a brief announcement okay
so U it's a course that will essentially
help you understand how geopolitics
really works from a professional
perspective not from the perspective of
opinion iions but how to actually
calculate National Power and how to uh
compare the difference differences
between the national powers of various
Nations and how to understand how the
world really works so it's all about
numbers it's all about hard facts and
figures no opinions no wishiwashi all
that stuff so this is an overview of the
course okay it's going to be about what
is geopolitics the international order
the state power energy the importance of
power and energy the West isent system
that system that we live in currently
the types of States forms of government
defining characteristics of nation
states building blocks of power I think
this is this is something that will
interest all of you comprehensive
National Power how to calculate any
nation's comprehensive National Power
based on facts and figures not opinions
okay U not opinions and sentiments but
actual hard figures then case studies
USA versus Russia USA China China Russia
India China India China Pakistan and so
on lots of case studies what is the
balance of power what is the national
interest this is what leads to conflict
between nations once again the different
kinds of Power then what are the types
of conflicts what are the root causes of
conflicts the ttis Trap the objectives
of conflict triggers for war and so on
and so forth okay Co conflict and war is
what actually drives geopolitics and the
struggle for power so I'm going to
explain all of that then obviously
cooperation as well what is hemony and
what causes the rise and decline of
powers in Nations so that's a brief
overview of the course uh the link is
going to be in the description I'll also
put the link in the comments so that uh
you all can find it let me do that let
me put the link in the comments so the
this course is going to go live on the
1st of February right now it's open for
pre-orders the link is
now in the live chat and you can all
access it from there here it is this is
the link and uh this is something that
uh this is a course that uh you can
sorry one second here it
is so this is something you can
pre-order right now if you pre-order now
before the 1st of February you will get
a reasonably good discount so go for it
uh this can I pin this let me see if I
can pin
this uh not sure if I can pin this
particular comment but uh here it is
it's it's there and you can you can see
it over here so whenever you you you can
if you want to if you want to go through
this it's obviously only for people who
are serious about understanding
geopolitics it's not for people who
don't have a serious interest in this
all right so that's that is it that's
the announcement it's going to go live
on the 1 of February whoever buys this
we have lifetime access to the course
and I'm going to come live on the 1st of
February and give an overview and
essentially take you through the entire
course and the course is a pre-recorded
course which you can study at your own
leisure in place in pace so there you
have it uh finally my course is about to
release about to launch on the 1st of
February so I hope that those of you who
are actually interested in in how
geopolitics really works how to actually
calculate the National Power of of
various Nations how to understand the
world order the picking order of world
of the various nations in the world how
to specifically point out each nation's
strengths and weaknesses Visa another
Nation or the coal strength and strength
and weaknesses of a coalition against
another Coalition that is all this
course will allow you to do it's going
to be something that will put you in the
top
5% of geopolitical analysts actually if
you study it properly so there you have
it check it out and I look forward to
seeing you there on the 1st of February
those of you who actually wish to
purchase this all right so uh with that
done let's go and so someone's asking
about promo code so right now if you
purchase before the first February you
will get an automatic discount so no
need for a promo code it's going to be
automatically applied to whoever uh
purchases the course right now so go for
it if you're interested and uh yeah the
promo code is already applied until the
1st of February once it's the 1st of
February it's going to be a different
price so right now those of you who want
it can get it for a discount all right
all right let's go and take some
questions
now uh MK Len says uh Global impact of
ram Mand uh look uh the Global impact of
ram Mand is is is that it's going it's
going to give a significant impetus to
what we call Hinduism or Hindu Dharma
right it's going to bring all all the
people together people from morus are
celebrating people from Fiji are
celebrating people in the US and various
other parts of the world are all
celebrating the fact that we have
reconstructed this this Temple after a
gap of nearly five centuries so it
brings the entire Global uh Hindu
Community together and it's going to
give a significant imped us and uh it's
going to give a significant incentive
for people to visit India and they will
once again start seeing India as the
spiritual Homeland they may live
wherever in the world we have millions
of Indians who live all around the world
you go anywhere in the world you will
find Indians okay you go to niagar Falls
you'll feel like you're in India and
nagara Falls is in India and there are a
few foreigners over there that's how it
feels Indians are everywhere so what it
it's going to do is it's going to give
them an incentive to return to India
it's going to you know once again
reposition India as the spiritual
Homeland the cultural Homeland and
Heartland of all Indian origin people
especially H dhic people Hindus Buddhist
SS Giants Etc okay so uh it's it's uh
going to turn aoda this small sleepy
until now small sleepy town of aoda into
a
global city with a global stature and
not just from the point of view of
Tourism but from the point of view of
culture and and
spirituality so you know we have so many
holy cities in India one of the holiest
obviously is Varanasi Banaras now Yoda
is going to reclaim it's it's one of its
possibly one of the preeminent positions
in that and that and and secondly so so
that's the cultural and spiritual thing
it's going to bring the Indian origin
people together it's going to give them
this uh new focal point Homeland
Heartland spiritual Place cultural Place
religious place right but it's also the
world has taken note of what's happened
okay and there's been a various there's
been various kinds of reactions lots of
these reactions have been negative
especially from the English speaking
media English speaking press the global
press there uh their reactions typically
are if you read if you read the guardian
or the New York Times or the New York
Post or Washington Post or whatever all
these BBC CNN all the all these things
even French Publications Etc whichever
what whichever Publications come under
the umbrella of of the so-called West
okay typically you will find that the
the sentiment is negative towards us
they are saying that India is descending
into Hindu supremacism and Fascism and
you know the standard tropes that they
that they employ to talk about India so
there's that but they they have taken
note of what's happened and their
reaction has been negative the reaction
mainly overall has been negative because
they don't want India to rise as a
civilizational power they would like
India to remain a nation state stay in
your lane so I just showed you the
geopolitical course that I've created
right okay and in that there is
something called types of State let me
put that back on since this is it's
relevant okay so uh where are we let me
the types of state right where is it
where is it where is it I'll show you so
here we have types of States we have
nation states we have kingdoms we have
Empire civilizations client states and
vasal States my favorite word right
vasal States
protectorates occupied States and failed
States and there are actually lots more
kinds of States but these are one could
say the main primary uh classific the
the primary classification of the types
of States so under the West fan system
that we live in the so-called rules
based World Order International order
every political entity Sovereign
political entity is regarded as a nation
state okay you will find that there are
various nations in the west like the UK
that don't have a constitution and are
actually monarchies they have a king or
a queen okay whether it is the UK
whether it is Spain whether it is uh the
Netherlands whether it is Lots I can
give you lots of other examples they all
have kings and queens they all have
royal families and yet they want us to
be a different kind of entity they want
us to be a nation state merely um
parliamentary democracy or any kind of
democracy but no monarchy even though
they have reserved and preserved their
their traditional systems okay so so
these are the different kinds of states
in the current Global Order every every
nation is regarded as a nation state
only but there are certain Nations that
have a deep and Rich history in
Civilization a few such Nations exist
one is India one is China even Russia
could be considered one so these are not
mere ly nation states these are
civilization States a civilization is
way greater and much broader than a
nation a mere nation state it can be
regarded as an artificial construct look
at the failed State called Pakistan it's
it's almost a failed State okay so
that's an artificial Nation Pakistan has
been artificially created by a foreign
power to serve a certain geopolitical
role another artificial Nation one could
say is the United States it's it's a
nation that was created out of settler
colonization and and Canada and all
these and so many nations so they want a
nation like India to remain merely a
nation state and not try to become too
big for it its
boots okay don't decolonize don't
reclaim your civilizational status right
and when a thing like the ram Mand
happens it's a step in towards
reclaiming India's civilizational status
okay today why don't we look at India as
a civilization because our laws are
foreign in nature our constitution is
foreign in nature the language we use to
communicate with each other is a foreign
language the education system the the
the government system the Judiciary the
bureaucracy the police force the Armed
Forces everything the structure the the
entire structure and base in the
foundation is foreign in nature and when
you start tripping away at this these
things and you bring back the indigenous
uh element in all of this that's when
you slowly start going towards the
status of a civilization and one of the
things we don't which doesn't exist is
that we don't have these great temples
which we had a thousand years ago all
across the length and the bread of the
country so now that one such Temple has
been rebuilt and certain other process
processes are in motion that's why there
is the world has taken note and that's
why there's been this strongly negative
reaction because they don't want this to
happen they want India to stay a mere
lowly nation state they don't want India
to become a civilization State because
they know that India is the oldest
civilization India is way greater
culturally and civilization than
anything that exists in the west the
only comparable Nation today is China
but China we know it's about 3,000 years
old we are God knows how many thousands
of years old at least 10,000 India from
the archaeological perspective from hard
archaeological evidence we are at least
10,000 years old China is three three
and a half thousand years old and China
doesn't have any problem in
acknowledging the fact that India is
older so there are two major
civilizational States today India is on
the way to becoming a civiliz ation
State China it is also somewhere on the
way to becoming a civilization State and
Russia one could say it's it's more of
an Empire than a civilization but yeah
one could say that it's got a broadly
Slavic perspective and is a big big
Slavic diaspora and so on so these are
the threats to to the Western LED World
Order and so that's why the reaction has
negative you know what's funny this
fellow this individual this Marauder
babber babber right he was from he was
not Indian we know that right I hope we
all know that babber was not Indian he
was usek I mean usbekistan as a nation
did not exist then but he was born in
the city of andon in the fana Valley in
usbekistan do you know you want to see
where it is where's the map where's the
map okay one of the most important
things in geopolitics is the map so let
me bring out the map and let's see where
it is it's not really far from India by
the way Central Asia is actually our
neighborhood but we have kind of of lost
touch completely with it so here we are
India Pakistan Afghanistan that is the
Indian subcontinent all right and then
we have
usone as you can see it's not really far
away it's a stone throw away from the
from a you know big perspective big
picture perspective and let's find the
city of Andy John where is Andy
John all right here we have Andy johon
so you can see that this got they have
this convoluted border and this here
City on the John is where Babar was born
all right so he was born there and he
came to India as an Invader as a
Marauder and as somebody who had no
respect for Indian culture and
civilization and he tried his best to
tear our civilization down obviously he
failed but one of the heinous things he
did was was that he destroyed the great
Ancient Temple that uh stood at the
which marked the location of the
birthplace of Sri Ram he destroyed that
and he built that that structure on top
of it right so now now the structure was
brought down in 1992 and this year 22nd
of January we have rebuilt and Recon
consecrated the D the pran prti of the
ram Mand so we have rebuilt our
civilizational you
know uh
Temple my question is this has there
been a single
protest from usbekistan
has there been a single protest from
usbekistan
has any usbek person
raised any concern about this or any any
any criticism about this has any usek
newspaper publication website Etc
criticized what's happened not one not
one they have no problem with India
bringing Justice back to its
land so why does the West have a problem
why can't they go and mind their own
business you know there is something
called sovereignty
there is something called non-
interference once again let me share my
course because it's it's relevant to
what I'm saying over here once again so
we have something called the
international order and the West fan
system so the the the foundational
pillars of the West F system are the
nation state system
sovereignty territorial Integrity non
intervention non-intervention means you
will not interfere in the internal
affairs of sovereign Nations I will mind
my business and do whatever I need to do
in my country and I will stay out of
your internal matters and you will
respect me and you will do the same you
will do whatever you want within your
country you will govern As You Wish pass
any laws any policies that you want and
you will stay out of my business in my
nation that that is the foundational
underpinning foundational pillar of the
rules-based world order and these
Western Nations H they they think that
they they can determine the rules as
they go as they go along today this is
the role tomorrow that's the role
certain things apply to me and they
don't apply to you certain things apply
to you but they don't apply to me this
is the hypocrisy that people sick are
sick and tired of and that's why the
West is declining because nobody
respects the West anymore so that's the
deal okay long answer but but that's the
point that's what it is all right let's
move on to the next question I'm sure we
have other questions lots of other
questions uh
abijit RI says how did how slash why did
Myanmar Burma brades adharmic country
behave so ad dharmically with respect to
Manipur you have no idea what's going on
in
Myanmar okay the problem is that we have
absolutely no understanding of what's
Happening across the border right now
and we don't have our textbooks don't
teach us our school schs our textbooks
our esteemed professors and teachers
they teach us nothing about our
neighboring countries so we have no idea
what's happening there and we get the
feeling that they are all our enemies or
they doing terrible things to us you
have to understand that Myanmar Burma
itself the northern part and other parts
of Burma themselves are under foreign
occupation so Manipur is facing a
terrible problem half of Manipur is
under foreign
occupation okay the occupiers are the
so-called cookie
and they have infiltrated from across
the border from Myanmar from myanmar's
territory if you look at satellite
images of the past five six years you
will see that in the southern part of
Manipur in the second Southern half of
Manipur thousands of new Villages have
cropped up in satellite images in over
the past five six years all infiltrators
from across the border okay because the
border is open that was the agreement
between India and Myanmar now why are
the burmes doing this is the question my
my my counter question to you is are
these infiltrators really burmes or are
they merely people who are coming from
burmes
territory let's look at the map of
course we should look at the map all
right where is the
map this is the larger question we have
to we have to
ask one second let me bring the map in
here we are
all right so as we know Myanmar Burma is
this large Nation reasonably large
Nation to our
East and significant portions of the
north of this
country are occupied or inhabited by
people who have nothing to do do with
burmes
culture so let's take the cookies is an
example well this term cookie is is a
neologism it's an artificial term that
has been created in in the past 100 150
years okay these
people their original tribal name was
Tado or something okay and these
individuals these people they don't
speak the Burmese language they don't
practice
burmes Customs or Traditions they don't
respect burm is customs or
Traditions religiously they are not
Buddhist or Hindu
and what are their
Origins these people they in the past 3
400 years less than 500 years they came
into Burma from western China
southwestern China which is the the Yan
region of
China okay so these people who are
invading Manipur right now are not
burmes they are fighting the government
of Burma they're fighting the government
of Bangladesh and they're fighting the
government of India they're fighting
three Wars in three countries and they
want their own Nation a nation in
Christ all right so the Burmese people
themselves are under siege from these
foreign
organizations you have the the arakan
issue the Rakin State issue you have the
Shan State the Karen State all kinds of
ethnic trouble in Burma they're all
fighting the burmes
government okay and then there are lots
of bigger Powers involved in this the
two big Powers involved in this in this
are the US and China okay the Chinese
are involved because China is right next
door okay as you can see if you if you
if you draw a straight line from the
border of Manipur and Myanmar and just
go straight
eastwards it's about China the Chinese
territory is just about 300 kilometers
away just about 300 kilometers away so
we have all this entire convergence of
issues problems over here and that is
the issue so the solution to the problem
in Manipur first of all we have to
understand the Manipur problem did not
occur in the last five years or 10 years
it the the roots of the problem that
Manipur faces today go back to the end
of the 18th century when the manipuri
king bhagia Chandra did a complete mess
of the succession he was a great king
okay he was a great king he was he was
great he was very big on culture the
Great eor Ence of manipuri culture that
happened is all because of King bhandra
bhandra manipuri dance not San all kinds
of things wonderful beautiful culture
but my question is what's the point of
having a beautiful culture if you can't
defend your territory and your
sovereignty and your territorial
integrity and demographic in Integrity
so what bhandra did was that he spent
all his attention on culture and art and
all that stuff and he did not specify
who should be be his successor when he
dies so when he died at the at the cusp
of the 18th and 19th centuries his sons
started fighting each
other to determine who will be the next
king so there was infighting among the
mes Manipur and then somebody took
advantage of that who took advantage the
burmes
kingdom okay not the Kookie Kingdom but
the burmes there was no Kookie Kingdom
the burmes Kingdom from Mandalay so they
invaded Manipur there was a seven years
of horrible devastation the king of
Manipur to escape into tripura or Assam
or something and after a few years he
was able to regain this Kingdom after
seven years in which Manipur suffered
horrific
atrocities but then the British came
into the picture because they were
already in in power in in in Bengal and
they came and you know brokered a treat
treaty a peace agreement between M the
kingdom of Manipur and the kingdom of
Burma and they were the guaran of the
peace which means that they were the
more powerful power the British
eventually they would go on to invade
and occupy Burma as well but they became
the major power in Manipur as well and
the King had to become a vasal of the
British and that's when all these
horrible things started the the British
started forcing the king to uh to settle
these troublemakers from across the
border in manipuri territory but even in
1900 or 1901 when the last when the
British British census happened less
than 1% of the population of Manipur was
kooki okay but today Manipur is overrun
by cookies and after 1947 the Indian
government continued the same stupid
British policies because they they did
not understand this region so the nugan
government just kept on applying the
same policies the same horrible practi
policies to Manipur so the people of
Manipur were the the indigenous people
of Manipur the mes were forced to live
in only 6% of the of their territory
infal the infal valley only 6% that is
legal apothide against the Hindus of
Manipur right so anyway so long story
short Myanmar
may be a dharmic country but these
cookies are not Myanmar is or dhic okay
they are foreigners even to Burma
they're foreigners even to Burma that's
the problem all right let's take some
questions from um uh from the comments
that people have posted earlier so let's
take
this Tushar and kinshuk your view on the
Iran Pakistan tensions does it matter to
our interests and can you put some
Spotlight on the Iran Pakistan tension
and recent action why so quick hot
flares and quick cool down what happened
what exactly is the deal right I mean so
quickly all this happened and suddenly
it's all cooled down is it natural is it
is it weird Is it
artificial that's the question so one
second let me
see yeah all right so first of all let's
take a look at the map because the map
is always our best friend if you want to
understand what's happening take a look
at the map so here we are map on the
screen here it is let's take a look at
at the two Nations Iran and Pakistan our
two na our two neighboring Nations
historically the Pakistan the current
Pakistan Iran Border historically used
to be the India Iran India Persia border
okay and let me just before I answer
this question let me put something in
context Iran
Persia has a rich history of at least to
3,000 years as a separate entity from
India okay the
ancient capital of Persia was called
persopolis that's what the Greeks called
it and that's what all the Western
writers call it but what did the
Persians call it what did the Persians
themselves call their capital city of
persopolis they called it
parur
parur all
right and this nation Persia which is
now called Iran it's historically been
called Persia where did the name Persia
come from it came from the word parha
the paraa people the Persians are the
parwa clan of the ancient Indians okay
and they migrated westwards long long
long ago and they settled this land
right next to India and they created
this big civilization here and
Persia whether it is during the eate
dynasty or other dynasties okay it was
always an expansionist aggressive
militaristic hegemonic Empire
tremendously powerful they fought the
Greeks they fought the Romans they
fought everybody
and they typically defeated everybody
they defeated the Romans one of the one
of the Roman emperors was taken prisoner
by the by the Persians and uh ritually
humiliated or whatever I not go into the
details okay if you are interested look
it up so these
Persians they were so vigorous so mighty
so powerful they had this expansionist
militaristic imperialistic tendency
always and they fought everybody my
question is why did the never fight
India why did the never even once go to
war with ancient India or try to invade
India
why that's the question I would like you
to think about I'm not going to answer
this question here but here we have Iran
and Pakistan as you can see Iran is a
larger
nation and Pakistan is a smaller Nation
but Pakistan I would say has about
twice I'd say Pakistan has about twice
the uh
population twice the population as Iran
roughly I would say most likely roughly
is it
Pakistan no Pakistan is three times the
population of Iran so Pakistan has less
land area but three times the population
now if you look at other uh other other
factors okay then Pakistan's military
strength is greater than that of Iran's
military strength and Pakistan's
economic strength is slightly less than
that of Iran
but if you
consider these factors together the area
the population the economic strength the
military strength and also nuclear power
and also power projection abilities you
take these factors together and
calculate and also the factor of energy
self-sufficiency if you take all these
factors together and you do the
calculation the secret calculation of a
nation's actual power you will find that
Iran is more powerful than
Pakistan Iran is
about 50% more powerful than Pakistan
cumulatively cumulatively but the
problem is that Pakistan has nukes and
Iran officially doesn't seem to have
nukes of course I suspect that by now
Iran has uh enriched sufficient uh
quantities of uh weapons grade uranium
to maybe
maybe uh construct 5 to 10 nuclear
warheads kiloton Warheads not megadon
but still you know I think Iran may be
an Undeclared nuclear power but Pakistan
has the Delivery Systems Pakistan has
Chinese designs of nuclear weapons and
they have well officially I don't know
130 something nuclear weapons officially
uh unofficially well we'll not go there
uh yeah so uh so that's the deal so
Pakistan has these
uh strengths it has certain weaknesses
it is not energetically self-sufficient
which means that it consumes more power
than it produces it has to import oil
and gas and petroleum and stuff like
that but Pakistan has a nuclear strength
it has a greater military strength but
overall Iran is more powerful the thing
is that they are roughly well matched
Iran and Pakistan the two nations are
roughly well
matched and uh so the situation is such
that neither Nation if it goes to war
can achieve a decisive or comprehensive
victory
it's always going to end in some kind of
stalemate so that's why there there's no
point for the two Nations it doesn't
make any uh logical sense for the two
Nations to go to war now what happened
is the question right why did the two
Nations have this issue so uh recently
our foreign minister Dr J Shanker was in
tan capital of Persia and I think it is
around this time or just after he left
something like that that Iran launched
crossborder missile strikes across the
Pakistan Iran Border into Pakistani
territory and targeted uh Pakistani
terrorist camps so as we all know
Pakistan is the World's Center of
terrorism uh per capita Pakistan has the
has by far the highest number of
terrorists in the world per capita and
uh uh Pakistan it's it's a mercenary
State it's not really a sovereign state
it's always been been on the payroll of
somebody or the other it's always been a
client State a vasal state of either the
US for some time it was China for about
a decade or so now it's back in the US
fold and their army is nothing but an
extension of the geopolitical agenda of
the more powerful Nation okay and of
course the Army itself has a certain
agenda they want to enrich themselves at
the cost of the people in the the nation
of Pakistan and they want to justify
their existence by painting India as the
big enemy or India doesn't care about
Pakistan we just want to be left alone
right
but that's how it is so Pakistan has is
known for Sheltering Terror terrorists
they have bled Afghanistan for decades
they have bled India for decades the
United States financed and funded
Pakistani terrorism in India for decades
we know it it's it's a known fact the
United States did that and today they
breach human rights and all that stuff
to us anyway that's a different story so
Pakistan has terrorists Pakistan has
targeted India for decades Pakistan has
destroyed essentially Afghanistan okay
since the 80s and Pakistan and Iran also
have this testy tense uh relationship so
before the AAS came to power in 1979 was
it 79 let's say if I'm wrong look up
Google it and find out the date the year
of the Persian Revolution the Iranian
Islamic revolution all right I don't
remember every date I think it's 79 1979
so before 79 there was a different
regime in power in Iran it was the Shah
of Iran Muhammad Rah pavi and this
gentleman Mr pavi was well he had a very
Pro US foreign policy he had essentially
opened his nation's uh petroleum
reserves and he had given a proper
Monopoly to the west to exploit these
resources and before before Mr pavi
there was a guy called Muhammad mad Who
had who was the Prime Minister he had
nationalized he had tried to nationalize
Iran's energy sector he tried to kick
out British petroleum and all that and
as a result of this he was regime
changed you know he was he was he was
regime Changed by the Americans by the
West standard modus operand standless
standard operating procedure whenever
there's a smish nation or or middle
middle power whose uh policies are kind
of not in line with the West's policies
affect the regime change very simple
that's what the the West does and then
they talk about democracy and freedom
and human rights so mosad was removed R
pahi was brought into power and in 1979
the AAS came to power they kicked out
Muhammad Rah pvi the the aahi was in
Exile in France very interestingly but
then he came back to Iran in 79 and
that's how the current regime in tan
came to power and it it it is still in
place in Iran it still rules
Iran so this is a very properly
Theocratic regime okay it's it's a shi
regime Shia Islam is the state religion
Pakistan Saudi Arabia all these other
nations are Sunni Nations so there's an
there's this religious angle religious
tension is there uh so there's that and
Pakistan is a us wasal and Iran is maybe
one could say a sworn enemy of the US
and Israel so Pakistan is is is has
great value to the US it serves as a
counterbalance and destabilizing factor
for India but also for Iran
it's fantastic isn't it to have a nation
that that that can serve this this kind
of purpose kill two birds with the same
Stone so that's what Pakistan does
that's the utility Pakistan has for the
US and for anybody who is willing to pay
enough but right now it's the US that is
the boss the master in Pakistan recently
the Pakistan chief of whatever staff
Army staff went to the US to Washington
to pay his respects and his uh salutes
Etc to his Masters uh so Pakistan can be
used in a variety of ways to destabilize
Iran and now we have to remember that
the border between Iran and Pakistan is
the border between the two divided
portions of baluchistan half of
baluchistan is under Pakistani
occupation the eastern part and the
western part of baluchistan is within
Iran's current territorial boundaries so
balistan is divided between two
Nations so if you are to the east of the
Border inside Pakistani territory you
have baloi people who speak the baloi
language you cross the border go west
into Iran you have the same people who
speak the same language okay interesting
so now the Iranians targeted certain
Pakistani terrorist positions the next
day the Pakistan is retaliated and
targeted Iranian positions and they said
that Iranians are keeping terrorist
anti- Pakistan terrorist outfits on
their soil that's what happened and then
the there was a brief breakdown of
diplomatic relations the two Nations so
The pakistanis Expelled the US
ambassador the the the Iranian
Ambassador and recalled their ambassador
from tan and then things kind of
simmered down settled down but things
are the the diplomatic relations are
back on track okay but the relations are
bad between the two Nations the two
Nations don't like each other they don't
trust each other the Iranians have no
love for Pakistan I promise you that and
that is a sentiment that is shared
across
the West Asia
region nobody in the Arabian Peninsula
has any
especially warm feelings towards
Pakistan uh the Saudis don't have any
great warmth towards Pakistan neither do
does anybody in the region so Pakistan
is kind of well almost failed state it
is it is propped up by the west by the
us because it has this utility as an
attack dog no uh uh no disrespect
intended for the
ordinary pakistanis but that's just a
matter of speech figure figure of speech
so Pakistan is this attack talkg and
that's what happened okay uh now it
makes sense for the two Nations to bring
the tensions down because neither nation
is in a position that it can fight and
defeat The Other Nation and if they go
to war it's going to be a ruinous War
just like the Iran Iraq war of the 1980s
which was kind of a proxy war Iraq under
Saddam Hussein was then a proxy of the
US and Saddam Hussein was instigated to
go to war with Iraq
with Iran and there was a nearly decade
long War which kind of ruined the
economies and infrastructure of both
Nations so when you have two nations of
roughly equal size roughly equal power
roughly and they go to war it's it's not
good for either
Nation so there are certain heuristics
one must use in calculating which nation
can actually win against another nation
and you need a certain amount of
strength relative strength to be able to
essentially get guarantee Victory so
yeah there you are so that's the deal
between Iran and Pakistan okay the the
relations are not good Iran doesn't like
Pakistan no one likes Pakistan Pakistan
has three neighbors India Afghanistan
and Iran neither of these neighbors
likes Pakistan neither of these
neighbors wants Pakistan there Iran the
Persians I would I would imagine would
be be way happier for that border to be
the India Iran Border and the pashun
would very much like Pakistan to break
up and they can retake pashtunistan
pakun so Pakistan is a is a Bas basket
case it's it's a a failed State it's
propped up by a western power the us
earlier it was the UK now it's the US in
in in between there was China also China
also still has some some interest in
Pakistan but that's how it is so
Pakistan is is a temporary nation and
that's where we are now let's take a
look at some questions from the live
chat all right let's let's remove this
here we are
all right
um uh what do we
have Dr Jay
Shanker yeah is it is it really
necessary to celebrate the 15th of
August and recall the thing that a great
nation like bat got independence from a
bunch of Islanders look you need certain
U
national
celebrations to as to serve as a focal
point and bring everybody together see
currently India has is a
nation uh that has a a tremendous amount
not a tremendous amount but a
significant amount of of division within
itself all these divisions have been
created during colonial times and there
are divisions of of Northern India
Southern India linguistic divisions and
God knows what all divisions religious
divisions lots of things have been
created to divide Indians among each
other okay and many people don't
identify with the indigenous
civilization and culture of India
they've adopted foreign religions and so
on I'm not complaining I'm just pointing
out a fact so now if you want certain
occasions to serve as a focal point to
unify everybody it makes sense to have
certain days like the 15th of August the
26th of January and whatever else may or
may not exist uh to serve as those
things obviously 15th of August 1947 was
not Independence Day it was dominan
status day it was dominan status day go
check out the actual facts
okay so it was dominant status day it
was not Independence Day and Pakistan
was given dominant status before India
so that India could not undo that and so
on and then India becomes a republic in
the year 1950 and the first and Mr Neu
is the first selected prime minister he
won the first election in the n in 50 or
51 or whichever Year please look it up
Google it yeah that's how it is so
obviously it's not Independence Day it's
nothing great to celebrate okay it is
the day that we were divided it is the
day our nation was partitioned we did
not even get independence and we we
never decolonized we have still kept the
same system lots of problems exist but
we still need certain days as focal
points to bring everybody together until
we become a more slightly more unified
nation in the future so I think it's all
right we the fact is that we were under
foreign occupation from a bunch of
Islanders for about 200 years and before
that for maybe three four Centuries by a
bunch of ragtag nomadic Turks but that's
just the way it is these are facts of
history and we should never forget this
history and we must we must learn the
right lessons from this history that's
what really matters so uh never forget
always keep this these things in mind
and as India progresses on the
civilization scale and becomes a
civilization State all over again or
over time then maybe we will have new
days that we will celebrate so right now
the 22nd of January for many Indians is
now a new Diwali year essentially so
such things will will happen more rather
than less and as as time goes by things
will evolve and things will change
that's just how I see
it all
right Rohit B says what's your take on
the current situation of Canada as a
nation and what's your opinion of its
economic and demographic future in the
coming one or two decades uh interesting
question let me take a seep of
water so what's the situation of Canada
as a nation
I don't know why everyone Chuckles when
when one talks about Canada so let's
let's go to the map where is the map let
us see the map so for those of you who
don't know Canada is one of the three
major nations in Northern in in North
America the continent of North America
which is divided from South America by
this by this region called Central
America so Canada is north of the us all
right it's it's uh larger in territory
in land area than the US
and you have this straight line border
which is typical of settler colonial
states which have been stolen from the
indigenous people you just draw straight
lines on the border so the situation of
Canada as a nation is this so this is my
perspective all right you may you don't
have to agree with it the way I see it
Canada is not a Sovereign
Nation it is
under us hegemony it is under US
economic hegemony it's under us
political hemony it's under US military
hegemony much more one would say than
the NATO Nations even these nations in
Western Europe with which are part of
NATO are under us political and Military
hemony and the EU States EU nations are
under US economic and political hemony
so all of these nations are under some
or the other form of us eimy even when
it comes to the nations of South America
they are all under usmany the Monro
Doctrine may be a thing of the 19th
century but it's it's extended augmented
version unnamed version perhaps still
exists and all these nations they make
sure that they don't do anything that
that displeases the US
significantly right so Brazil can be a
member of breaks but they don't take to
cross certain lines that would
significantly displease the us otherwise
there'll be significant consequences for
the leadership and then things will be
taken care of so Canada is what I would
say a client state of the US it's an
extension of the US it's a puppet state
of the US Mr there is no actual
political leadership in Canada uh when
it comes to Canada if you look at the
actual laws and the way the laws are
written in Canada even if you own land
or territory or or or house or property
in Canada you are only leasing it you
don't own it really so then the question
is who owns this land of Canada and the
answer is the P the force the power The
Entity the person that owns the land in
Canada is the crown of England it is
which is currently King
Charles so King Charles owns Canada by
the way King Charles also
owns
stria
Australia and who owns England well who
owns England Washington DC owns England
in the UK so the
center of power right now globally
especially in so-called West is the US
it's Washington DC all right so yeah
these are all layers upon layers upon
layers of layers upon layer of all these
things that are very hard to visualize
and be aware of but that's how it is so
the way I see it Canada is a puppet
state of the US Canada is Sovereign only
in name Canada is not really Sovereign
Justin Trudeau justtin Trudeau yeah
Trudeau not Bieber Trudeau doesn't
really have any actual power or whoever
will eventually replace him they will
not have any actual power just like
Rishi sunak doesn't have any real power
just like Olaf Schultz doesn't have any
real power and so on okay all these
nations are puppet States so is Canada
Canada is a puppet state its
sovereignty index from 0o to one is zero
it's zero so that's how I see it what's
the other other part of the question
economic demographic future well it will
serve the interest in the agenda of the
US demographically I believe that they
are giving Visa not not not visas but
passports on arrival to PE to certain
flavors of immigrants the moment they
reach the airport and they walk off the
plane they giving they given passports
caran passports but only certain kind of
people only certain kind of diversity is
allowed so that nonsense is is already
happening in Canada and I don't have a
greatly
optimistic uh Outlook towards the future
of Canada sadly I mean Canadians are
really nice people if you come across a
person anywhere in the world who has a
North American accent but who is really
nice it's going to be a Canadian not you
know what okay Americans are really
aggressive Brash people loud people
opinionated people pushy people
Canadians are really polite Canadians
are really well behaved I'm not saying
all Americans are not well behaved but
you get the point on average so
Canadians are really nice people overall
but there you have it that's the
situation in Canada right now Canada is
not a Sovereign Nation and one wonders
what is going to happen to its
demographics well anyway it's a settler
colonial state it's a land that's stolen
from the natives the natives have been
horrifically marginalized I don't even
want to talk about what is what is still
being done to the natives okay not
second class but third class citizens in
North America especially in nonurban
Canada so well so there's nothing for
them to complain about I mean the
Canadian majority demographic they have
nothing to complain about come on don't
complain uh anyhow there we
are okay one has to answer this question
at least once in a
session can India take over Pakistan
occupied
Kashmir okay let's compare India and
Pakistan let's compare the the the the
the what shall we call it let's
compare the National Power of India with
that of
Pakistan so first of all let me put the
map on the screen because it will show
you the scale of the two Nations I'm
sure everyone in India knows what
Pakistan looks like but let's anyway put
it on the screen so here we have India
versus Pakistan the two Nations on the
screen so if we look at uh if you look
at the land area Pakistan is no match to
India if you look at the population
Pakistan is no match for India so
overall from that perspective India is
about four to five times more massive
than Pakistan if you take the factors of
population and land area together if you
talk about economic strength India is
like 10 times more powerful than
Pakistan economic strength if you talk
about military strength India is about
nine times more powerful than Pakistan
just military strength nuclear strength
as per the official narrative Pakistan
has slightly more nukes than India
apparently well if you if you watch one
of my older Indian interest
episodes uh you will find that I have
demonstrated conclusively that India has
enough sufficient sufficient file
material for more than 3,000 nuclear
warheads but anyway let's let's go by
the official figures so Pakistan has
slightly more nuk than India and India
has way more power projection ability
than Pakistan if you put all this
together and Pakistan is not a Sovereign
Nation it's a wasal state of the US
India is a Sovereign Nation genuinely so
if you look at all this together the
Indian overall National Power is way
larger than that of Pakistan more than
three times larger than that of Pakistan
economic comparison no match Pakistan is
no match military comparison no match
the only
factor is the nuclear dimension so
Pakistan is a nuclear weapons power
whether they have 10 or 160 doesn't
matter they have
nukes okay and that's that's one of the
X factors in geopolitics if you're
nuclear weapons power all calculations
change you may be significantly weaker
than another Nation you may be
significantly smaller than another
Nation you may be economically crippled
compared to another Nation but if you
have nukes that Nation will have to
think 300 times before taking certain
actions against you so Pakistan has
nukes we know that they got the nukes
from China and Europe long story so the
question then is can India take over
Pakistan
P India can okay uh I think po may not
even be the Pakistan Army's Red Line the
Pakistani Army's Red Line most likely
will be Punjab you know LA or or r pendi
or or a significant breakout of Pakistan
if you take back Po in in a lightning
move
they it may be over before they realize
it but the question is does India want
to take such risks does India want to
get embroiled in a major military
confrontation right now especially when
you have the China Factor as well which
is the Real Enemy Pakistan just leave it
alone for now that's what I would say
Pakistan is not a threat to India it's a
nuisance it's a nuisance it's like that
okay let's not make that comparison it's
like it's a nuisance Pakistan is a
Nuance it it can you know
periodically at a certain frequency
sporadically keep on hurting India to
certain to a certain extent and then we
have to calibrate our responses
accordingly the main thing is that there
are so many internal factors within
Pakistan that that create this this
Force this this Force within Pakistan
that that threatens to break it apart so
there is very little internal cohesion
and Harmony in Pakistan Sy wants
Independence balistan wants Independence
K pakun wants reintegration with with
Afghanistan
P gilg balistan these people they want
to come back to India because they can
see across the border how much
everything is developed how how much
happier the people are so these forces
eventually will at some point in time if
uh under circum under certain
circumstances they will spontaneous ly
lead to the breakout of Pakistan the
only thing that's keeping Pakistan
together is the foreign power it was the
US then it was China and the US now so I
would say all we have to do is not fight
Pakistan right now not do anything
unilaterally right now just focus on
economic and Military
growth we need to first of all our next
Target first Target should be becoming
the third largest economy in the world
right now India is number five we need
to become number three leap FR Germany
and Japan that will happen in the next
three two three years then we have to
become a$1 trillion economy and as your
economic might growth your military
grows your military might also grows and
once you reach a certain level nobody
will want to actually in the right mind
want to fight you in any any way what
whatsoever so that's what India needs to
do so right now forget about po give it
five or 10 years Pakistan is a temporary
nation in a few years the Pakistan Iran
Border will be the India Iran Border
it's going to happen
okay it could be 5 years it could be 50
years but it's going to happen so there
we have it patience my friends F
patience
huh A2Z Vlogs what about the
semiconductor sector of India well we
are investing significantly in that I'll
not go into the details because it's a
very very large topic very vast topic
but we are the Indian government is
investing significantly in the
semiconductor sector it it is one of the
ctors of special uh of special
focus and I have an entire podcast uh on
the channel uh about semiconductors it
it it came out pretty recently uh so
please check it out and you'll get many
of your answers in
there McLovin is the USA going into a
civil war well well well what can I say
what's happening in the US yeah okay
let's let me bring the map back to the
United States of Americas of America
Estados
unidos Estados unidos so why am I
speaking in Spanish it's because of the
Southern border the Biden regime has
opened up the southern border and it's
allowing anybody to cross into the US uh
I don't know what the figures are it
looks like in the last year more than
two or3 million apparently you can check
out you can do your own D due diligence
and check the figures it looks like
around 3 million illegal immigrants were
allowed to enter the US and they are not
only allowed to enter the US they are
given documentation identification and
they are settled in various parts of the
US that's what the Biden regime is doing
and the Texas government Texas is a
state it's the largest state in the US
the Lone Star State the Texas government
has decided to put up razor wire across
the across the border okay now this is
not a state border it's an international
border so the Biden
regime is is has told the Texas
government
to stop doing this and hand back control
of the international border to the uh to
the uh Central forces let's say and
Texas has refused and Texas has I
believe accused Biden and his regime of
high
treason and all the states where they
have Republican majorities are
supporting
Texas okay so I'm not saying that the us
is going to go into Civil War but the
the these this looks like the initial
stages of something that happened in the
19th
century that's why everyone's talking
about Civil War right
now because Texas is refusing to obey
the orders of the White
House and they're doubling down on
securing their border and the question
is how can the US
government insist on doing something
that is blatantly illegal according to
their own laws
let's say somebody from India wants to
immigrate to the US you have to go
through the proper
procedures you have to apply for a
Visa answer all their questions provide
all the paperwork then you go there on a
certain kind of Visa then you to wait
for 78 years to get a green card and
then another 300 years to get a
citizenship but for certain flavors of
immigrants you can just cross across the
southern border across the Rio
Grande come into the US and you're given
you know paperwork immediately documents
driver's license whatever documentation
is given and then you are settled in
some City nice coity in the US on
taxpayer
money and so on and I'm allegedly some
of these people may even be allowed to
vote if you have certain kinds of
identification you can
vote you may even become part of the
police force so that's the kind
of absolutely blatantly crazy thing the
Biden government is doing the Biden
regime is doing and Texas has put its
foot down and you know what what's funny
you know what's
funny India had invited the geriatric
President
Biden as a curtsy to be the chief
guest in yesterday's Republic Day
celebrations in New Delhi today is the
27th of January yesterday was India's
Republic Day 26th of January so India
had invited Biden he had accepted but
but then there was this issue the
Americans accused India of try of
allegedly attempting a hit on a US
supported
terrorist gur patwan panu or whatever
the hell his name is okay he's a
terrorist who is apparently a CIA agent
who's an anti-india terrorist he is
threatened to blow up India's Parliament
and to blow up Indian planes Air India
planes so the Americans shelter this
sort of people okay and the they have
accused India of Alle legely trying to
kill this guy on us soil a US citizen on
us soil so because of this diplomatic
issue Biden then pulled out of the
Republic Day
thing and then M makon of France very
kindly agreed to step in and he was
yesterday's Republic Day guest in New
Delhi what's funny is that Biden refused
to come despite accepting earlier but
the governor of
Texas the governor in the us is like the
chief minister in India so the governor
of Texas was in New Delhi he attended
India's Republic Day Celebrations even
though Biden refused to come and right
now his state is is involved in a
standoff against the White House so I
would not say we are in a civil war
situation right now but certain lines
are being drawn right now certain very
rigid lines are are being drawn right
now and the most incredible thing is
that the US government the White House
wants to do things that are completely
illegal ACC according to US law the US
is no longer a nation of laws
clearly it's a nation in in very bad
decline very bad social decline very the
standards have dropped so badly my God
the one thing about the US in the 1950s
and 60s even the 70s was the standards
by against which they held themselves
there was something called American
exceptionalism that was their National
ideology today it's American mediocrity
the lower the depths we Plum plump the
happier we
are so yeah that Nation I don't have I
don't know what to say it's not a nation
in Decline from a power perspective it
is way ahead of any other nation in
terms of hard power okay and terms of
power projection no one can match it
China is not even a match even one third
of of the US okay China is nowhere near
the US not even close but in terms of
Standards the nation the US is in
Decline and it's typically there that
the decline begins in an Empire look at
the history of the Roman Empire where
did did the decline begin not in the
hard power the decline started in the
standards so you have a decline in the
standards of the US it's it's becoming
increasingly a nation of progressively
lower standards and the kind of
government they have is is uh ridiculous
so there we are so not yet a civil war
but yeah people are now speaking openly
of a civil war well
sad
okay um Natasha says had come across the
info that Texas is not about of the US
it's part of its it has its own
Constitution as well I think um yeah I
don't know I can't recall whether they
have have the non Constitution but if
you have seen it it may be so so I would
I would urge the viewers to check it out
even I will check it out does why don't
we do it live yeah let's go to our good
friend Google and check out whether
Texas like Natasha says I'm sure she's
right whether Texas has its own
Constitution Texas Constitution let's do
it
Texas my spelling Texas
Constitution the constitution of the
State of Texas is the document that blah
blah blah blah blah handwritten blah
blah Wikipedia is not a reliable source
of information but I'm just looking at
it for the sake of very rapid
convenience so yes I am it's pretty
clear that Natasha is 100% right Texas
has its own Constitution but it is a
part of the us so that's where I would
disagree Texas is a part of the us it's
part of the Union you know before the
Civil War in the mid 19th
century uh they used to refer to the
United States
as the United States
are
after the Civil War they changed that to
say the United States is not are so it
became a single entity instead of a of a
plural uh kind of entity um so so Texas
is indeed a part of the us it's one of
the 50 states but Texas has always been
this this this state with a mind of its
own the Lone Star State and there have
been calls sporadically for the
secession of Texas from the US way after
the Civil War ended even in the 20th
century I'm sure other states may also
have their constitutions in the US uh so
you know the fact about the US is this
the US is a settler Colonial Nation it
is a nation that was created out of
somebody else's land and territory and
it was it was settled by replacing the
native indigenous population of this
region the natives have been essentially
wiped out and whoever is still alive is
badly marginalized so it is a settler
Colonial Nation it's an artificial
Nation uh Pakistan we know is an
artificial Nation so so is the US so is
Canada and so are many of the Nations
that are post Colonial or settler
Colonial nations in the
Americas uh so when you have an
artificial Nation the and a nation
that's made of immigrants from God knows
what part of the world then there is
very little they have in common even the
language now is not that much in common
the I think the Spanish language is one
of the major languages in the US
definitely the number two language and
so on and there is very little cultural
or or ethnic connection between all the
people in the US lots of different eth
ethnicities lots of different linguistic
backgrounds lots of different cultural
backgrounds so what do they have in
common very little they have a
constitution they have laws and all it's
a nation of laws it's a nation of police
police enforcement it's a police state
the US is a police state by the way you
go to New York City you take away the
cops for 50 see if you go to New York
City you will see cops everywhere
everywhere everywhere every single
anywhere you look you will see cop cars
and cops you take away the cops the
police from New York City for 15 minutes
the city is going to descend into riots
the US is a police state it's held
together by force the force is something
you see everywhere but but you don't pay
attention to okay so some people would
say that Iran is a police state yeah
sure so is the US the US much more than
than
Iran so it's an artificial nation and
artificial Nations typically don't last
forever civilizations can last for
thousands of years Rome is an Empire
lasted let's say, 1500 years roughly
especially the Eastern Roman Empire the
bantine Empire Istanbul
Constantinople but uh the US it's
already in Decline the standards are are
are badly in Decline there you have it
okay let's take let's talk about
something
else as says the same police killed an
Indian girl yes I do remember recall
something some Indian girl being shot
and then the the cop was laughing at the
fact that he killed the girl yeah police
brutality is is part for the course in
the US unfortunately sadly sadly for the
people but yeah okay let's take a
question from the previous
comments this is by Ren again have you
heard about free Burma Rangers Operation
1107 and operation 1027 in Burma so
circling back to Manipur we were talking
about Manipur sometime ago let's go back
to Manipur what is this free Burma
ranges nonsense it's a Christian
organization probably based out of the
US whose only Purp
purp is to convert the
people of the places they operate in to
Christianity so they are actively doing
this in this war zone in Burma right now
there a civil war going on in Burma
foreign sponsored Civil War so these uh
free Burma Rangers individuals they are
active in Burma and they are they are uh
in embedded within the anti-government
forces which means the non- burmes
forces that are occupying Burma and also
parts of Manipur
okay and they their agenda is to convert
as many people as possible to to
Christianity so that is free Burma
Rangers that shows the kind of us hand
there is in what's happening in in Burma
and by extension in India's Far East in
in Manipur okay and they're specifically
targeting Manipur because Manipur is the
large is the last non-converted
population in India's Far East even
though when it comes to the mes about
two and a half lakhs recently have got
converted to Christianity so they are no
longer
M yeah you convert to a foreign religion
you not are no longer part of the
indigenous culture that's as simple as
it is and if the Maes don't realize it
they need to wake up pretty
quickly so so the free Burma Rangers are
these R Evangelical uh imperialist
American organization that is involved
in you know interfering in the internal
affairs of a Sovereign Nation Burma
Myanmar uh operation 1107 operation 10
27 so it's uh these are dates 1107 which
means November 7 and 1027 probably means
uh October 27 so these are various
anti-government operations military
operations that are active in Northern
and Eastern Etc parts of Burma there are
I think
three
uh military outfits Insurgent outfits
terrorist outfits whatever you want to
call it there are active three major
outfits one is the arakan Army then
there is uh there there are these you
know other other organizations that are
supported by China all the US and they
are part of the cookie influx into India
uh and so on so these are all and and
they have had great success these two
operations 1107 one27 they've had great
success in against the Burmese
government in the last let's say three
months they have been able to capture
significant amounts of territory from
the Burmese government from from the
military hun in
Burma and apparently there is some
element of Chinese support in this so I
think the Chinese are trying to put the
government of Burma in in a
disadvantageous position so that they
can
extract concessions from them so what do
the Chinese want in this so the Chinese
obviously see Burma as a resourcer
country that they can exploit for
natural resources and Burma has a very
nice very long Maritime boundary and the
Chinese want to establish ports in in
places like Rakin state was it sit was
it where was it I think it
was okay I don't remember where it was I
can look it up later but somewhere in
the Rakin State the Chinese want to
establish a major port a deep water Port
which can enable them to keep an eye on
what's happening in the Bay of Bengal
region and give them power projection
abilities in this region so right now
they don't have any such play they have
hban TOA which is kind of well uh which
which is no longer very much under their
control control the way they would like
it to be they would like more control
it's not so and the lak the the
maldivian government is currently uh
cooperating with China and giving them
uh certain uh you know incentives and
things but one wonders how long that
lasts so the Chinese want more options
they have a port in jibuti a military
base in jibuti in the Horn of Africa
right right to the south of Yemen across
the straight of bab Al mandb between the
Gulf of Adan and the Red Sea and the
Chinese want at least one port in
Myanmar so if they can place the
government of Myanmar Burma in a
significantly tight spot in a very
disadvantageous position then they can
extract big concessions from them and
then bail them out so these
anti-government forces some of them they
all get their arms and ammunition from
China by the way okay China is the place
from which where the arms and ammunition
is coming and all of that is is pouring
into Manipur also by the way okay the
Chinese are playing multiple games
they're playing a complex game they
probably do want the government in Burma
to stay on the military government but
they want to squeeze it they want to
pressurize it to extract concessions
they want to destabilize India as a
result they want to keep the Americans
as far away as possible even though they
are already involved in this matter so
so that's a situation so these
operations are ongoing operations they
are reasonably successful operations in
Burma the free Burma Rangers are the
American presence in Myanmar these two
operations are kind of there's a Chinese
hand to some extent in these
operations all
right kiruma suichi
hirumi says was baluchistan ever part of
proper Indian civilization not greater
Indian civilization like Iran shinjang
Central Asia but proper Indian
civilization have you heard of the
parata Raj Dynasty
parat Raj
Dynasty let's let's look it up shall we
let's look it up uh let us go to our
best friend Google and we shall do a
Google
Search and we shall try and search for
the parata Raja Dynasty p a r a t a r a
j a d y n a s t
y and what do we get parata rers so what
does it
say or paraj was the D of parthan kings
of course everything has to be Iranian
or parthan in the territory of modern
day Western Pakistan which is
beluchistan by the way all right so
let's take a look at
imagis now does this look like a Persian
image to you my dear friends is Persia
is Zoran Persia well known for this
specific symbol called the
swastic here is another coin from the
parat rajes again a swastic again a
swasti and here I'm not sure sure what
it is but here we have it so there you
have it these were these were an Indian
Dynasty uh and of course there's an
element of of Persian influence there'll
be an element of skan influence and so
on so forth it was this is the the Far
East the the far west of India so India
and Persia were always always neighbors
and it was the the balistan region west
of Sy that was typically the evolving
boundary of India and Persia boundaries
are never are never static they always
change from time to time Century upon
Century decade upon decade the parat
rajas ruled in baluchistan roughly 2,000
years ago roughly roughly give or take
and they clearly had Indian iconography
symbology on their coins okay so listen
do your own research I'm just G showing
you the direction so I gave you this
name the parat Raja Dynasty go and
search for it go and look up the history
see who which Dynasty came before them
see which Dynasty came after them and
see the continuity the cultural and
civilization continuity so that's how
you do your
own research all
right G study says please introduce
yourself
in hooker uh
dad uh Harish har does Putin W Alaska
back well eventually why
not but what Putin really wants was a
res is a Resurgence of Russia and the
stabilization of of Russia's uh zone of
influence so every Empire every
civilization has an extended zone of
influence which is cultural economic and
Military influence including a Zone an
extr territorial extr territorial zone
of exclusive influence where nobody else
dare intrude and the Americans have
dared intruded dared intrude into
Russia's exclusive Zone Z Zone by trying
to support Ukraine and we are seeing the
consequences of that so does Putin want
Alaska back I would say that Alaska is
far far from his mind he he may joke
about it but he wants to stabilize and
consolidate Russia's extr territorial
exclusive zone of
influence all right okay please answer
my question next all right what's your
question I need to find a question there
are there's a million questions here and
I'm not able to find I've scrolled
through a lot so if I see it I'll answer
it but I did see your question this one
um okay oh what
else
[Music]
um Benzene do we think do you think we
are doing the right thing by supporting
Israel are we supporting Israel look
when it comes to uh voting in the
UN India typically abstains from votes
about Israel Palestine India sometimes
even votes for Palestine and against
Israel once in a while and when it comes
to uh condemning terrorist activities
India will always condemn terrorist
activities so India is not explicitly
supporting Israel versus Palestine but
if you look at look this is just the
logic of strategy this is how
geopolitics works you have you means you
as a nation every nation has a very
clear set of of national interests okay
National interest every nation has
national interests a set of national
interests there are vital interests
there are important interests and there
are peripheral interests peripheral so
vital interests are a certain category
of interest and so on so forth so every
nation knows what its interests are now
you want to do whatever it takes to
further and Advance your interests right
so I want to advance my interests my
friend Israel wants to advance his his
interests my other friend Persia wants
to advance as everybody wants to advance
their interests now I have to see that
my interests can be advanced in these
manners which other nations exist around
me where we have a convergence of
interests where we want more or less the
same thing and we have more or less the
same kind of threats so if you look at
these these factors together you'll find
that India and Israel have a tremendous
amount of convergence so then why would
India not work together with Israel
there is no right or wrong in
geopolitics there is no morality in
geopolitics this is wrong this is right
no no no no no there is no space for
Morality and sentiment and all these
things in geopolitics it's all
about prioritizing your National
interest that's all it is and we are
doing absolutely the right thing by
prioritizing our national interest India
first India first always and whoever
will work with us we will work with them
and we'll support them so that's how it
goes
right sorab Sina says why are we failing
in jet engines importing from the West
in Russia is not the way we can proceed
strategically I guess I'm not sure what
you mean by proceeding strategically but
let me answer the question which is very
good question why are we failing in jet
engines look we haven't failed in jet
engines we uh we have the GT gas turbine
derine research establishment or
whatever it is called in Bangalore they
have been working on an engine called
Cav they have achieved a certain amount
of thrust the engine works you can use
that in certain class of aircraft you
can use it in missiles you can use it in
drones so the engine works the question
is how much thrust do we actually
want so it has I don't know how much 60
70 kiltons of thrust or something it
works but we want 120 or let's say we
want 110 or let's say we want 95 kilot
kiltons of thrust we want a certain
amount of thrust and we have achieved a
certain amount of thrust why are we not
able to achieve that we will achieve it
but it takes time look at the
development life cycle of the foreign
engines the French engines the
rollsroyce engines in the UK the
American engines the Russian engines and
so on they have been iteratively
developing these engines for the past 70
years the first jet engines were
developed in
Germany I'm suppose you know it those
were Pulse jet engines I believe they
were used on the V2 cruise missile the
world's first cruise missile and so I'll
not go into the history it takes decades
to develop this technology we have done
a reasonably good job at achieving what
we've achieved right now but what we
need is we need a Quantum Leap we need
to very quickly develop an engine that
we can use in certain kinds of fighter
jets so the Tes is a single engine jet
then you will have
um Advanced medium combat of amca
there's a tbda
twin
engine
TBF twin engine deck based fighter which
is supposed to take off and land in from
aircraft carriers and so on and so forth
there is the
amca um so on so some of these will be
dual engine twin engine aircraft some of
them will be single engine aircraft and
we have certain other things also coming
up I'll not talk about those so we have
a certain capacity our engine can
produce a certain amount of thrust
certain amount of thrust but we need a
different kind of thrust so it makes
sense if possible to acquire the
technology for somebody else now I'll
tell you something if you look at
history no Nation ever transfers jet
engine technology to any other Nation
even very friendly Nations don't do that
and now there's talk about France
possibly uh the French uh French company
saf they probably are in talks with the
Indian government with the French
government in Indian government is the
interface uh to transfer jet engine
technology to India
um I think we're in the initial phase of
the talks I am not extremely optimistic
about this so the point is this that you
know jet engines are extremely
complex machines and the temperature and
pressure within a jet engine is
ridiculously high the temperature and
pressure is such that it will easily
melt
steel now the the the the turbine inside
the jet engine it has blades okay you
suck in air from the from the front you
inject a fuel fuel air mixture you
ignite that and that explosive ignition
produces the thrust and it also drives
the turbine blade which generates
electricity and sucks in more air so
it's kind of a self- sustaining to some
extent mechanism but the temperature and
pressure inside is ridiculously high it
will melt steel then what do we use
inside as the material for for for the
turbine blades and the and the ex the
casing and all that what do we
use so in the west they use single
Crystal
Alloys the entire
blade a single blade of the turbine is
grown as a single metallic alloy Crystal
it's a very specific process that's used
for this and the technology in the
technological knoow you need to to
develop this to be able to do this takes
a lot of time it takes decades to
develop and they have invested the
decades whereas we did not invest the
decades our previous governments did not
prioritize did not prioritize jet engine
development so now the Modi government
is now being told that you need to do
this in the next two years all this
pressure from all across the Indian
citizenry everyone is saying oh we have
been doing this for decades no we have
not been doing
anything the Tas aircraft itself was the
the development project was stalled for
decades it was conceived in the 80s
1980s so why did it only take off after
vaj came to power and again it was dead
for a decade and so on so the point is
the governments in the past have made
have done their best to Scuttle India's
indigenous defense uh manufacturing
capabilities because they wanted to
import arms ammunition Etc from the west
from abroad and take Kickbacks of
allegedly so there we have it so uh
hopefully this Indo French thing works
out then we can you know just acquire
the knowhow and start building our own
engines or if it doesn't work out which
is possibly more likely then we have to
be prepared to spend a decade or two uh
perfecting the jet developing the jet
engine technology even the Chinese they
still use Russian engines the Saturn
engine and whatever other engine their
jet engines still don't work
properly okay their jet engines still
have a very short life so the ch Chinese
themselves are struggling with this
Indians have this great regard for
Chinese right well they themselves are
struggling with jet engine technology
okay okay long enough question let's
take some more
questions um um Mr
Schmid I'm sorry what on Earth I'm not
talking about shaan sorry about that the
first jet was the M Schmid
but okay yes you are right there were
the stukas the FY wolfes the me Schmidts
the HL
so many of these German incredibly
Advanced for their time fighter planes
but yeah one of the me mids was the
first jet engine plane but if I am not
mistaken I could be mistaken but if my
memory serves me right the first jet
engine was used on the V2 cruise missile
possibly before it was used on the mmith
possibly I may be wrong but yeah it's a
it's a good point you made the M schmith
you pointed out over here it's an
interesting plane and I would encourage
people who are interested in aviation in
history and all this check it
out okay where are we oh once again
P how many times do answer the P
question chirag aast says how can we say
India France relationship will be a
separate poll such as Russia China in
future keeping in mind us as their big
daddy can they free how can they break
free of Us control okay for that we have
to go and check out the
map so that we understand the French
perspective of the
world so one second let me put the map
where's the map where's the map here's
the map so we talking about France
France is this nation in Western Europe
now I will go ahead and
say that France from the perspective of
overall National Power is the most
powerful nation in Western Europe if we
disregard the fact that most of these
nations are not completely Sovereign in
the case of Germany it is not sovereign
at all it has a sovereignty of zero
because it is under permanent US
military occupation France is
not and France has its own independent
nuclear deterrent its own nuclear
warheads M to French nuclear missiles
that are sitting inside French nuclear
submarines that are on permanent Patrol
worldwide the French have their own
nuclear deterrent the UK's nuclear
deterrent is a deterrent in name only
the UK's nuclear warheads are M to
American missiles which means that the
big red button is in Washington not in
the hands of Mr Rishi sonak
sadly so France is the only nation in
Western Europe which is either EU member
or a NATO member that has a quasi
independent foreign policy France has a
significant amount of power projection
in Western Africa in the sahil region of
Africa the entire
fanone region of Africa okay they have a
strangle hold on the economies of many
of these nations through the through the
CFA Frank that comes in two flavors we
have spoken about that many times before
and the French also have significant
possessions in the Indian Ocean region
for example the French Southern
Antarctic
lands and so on Islands this is a
British possession I believe but this is
a French possession the French Southern
and Antarctic
Islands okay uh which is kind of north
of Antarctica and southeast of
Madagascar and we have some some other
Islands as well I'm not sure who this is
South Africa all right that's fine uh
this Al okay this also could be yes
French island there we have it French
islands and also we also have what we
know is reun which is a French
possession okay reunion is French po I'm
not sure who I think it could be morus
yeah it's part of
morus and uh La could be
morus yes sels is independent now but it
was once in the
French you whatever uh thing
mayot I can't recall who owns it but my
point the point I'm trying to make is
that France has a significant
interest geopolitical interest power
projection interest in ter iial interest
in the Indian Ocean region they also
have a significant amount of influence
in the Southern Pacific okay uh many of
these little Nations and Islands French
Polynesia for example Baba for example
and so on there's a certain amount of
French interest there also so if we if
you take all of this into consideration
you could say that France France has a
significant amount of power projection
ability they I don't know how
many aircraft carriers they have shall
we find out let's find out how many
aircraft carriers they have please give
me a second I shall put Google on the
screen uh French aircraft carriers they
have nuclear submarines okay uh number
of French
nuclear submarines how many do they have
okay they have six which means that at
least two are on petrol at any given
point in time how did I come up with
this number of two do some homework
French aircraft carrier so if you have X
let's say n number of of Naval assets at
any given point in time on average oneir
of those
are operationally deployed only one
third that's how it goes aircraft
carriers how many do they have 15 but
what is the current situation only one
shall the goal okay so the French have
one aircraft carrier in six nuclear
submarines which which is I would say
very respectable yes
so as you can see they have a
significant uh geopolitical reach they
have significant amount of power
projection they can enforce power
projection through their Naval strength
reasonably good Naval strength they have
a good nuclear deterrent and so on so
and they have a quazi independent
foreign policy and they do not see the
us as a friendly Nation if you ask fren
French intelligence
privately you will see a very
interesting perspective come out from
there France does not see the us as a
Nation it sees the us as an adversarial
Nation as as a
rival okay so that's why the French are
so so uh happy to work together with
India because there's this tremendous
convergence of interests we in India
have a significant interest in the
stability and the safety of the Indian
Ocean region we see it as our strategic
backyard and we are now beginning to
develop the naval might to actually turn
it into our actual strategic backyard
not just in words but de facto strategic
backyard and that zone of influence of
ours it intersects with the zone of
interest of the French because they also
have possessions there and why not work
together and it helps us it helps them
as well and they would like they would
like to tap into India's gigantic and
growing economy and we want military
equipment we want technology we want all
kind of things so we can certainly work
together so um I don't say in the India
France relationship will be an actual
separate poll but it's going to be a
very important geopolitical factor going
forward so yeah that's how I see it the
can the French Break Free of Us control
uh not any time in the immediate future
suddenly the the US is way way way too
powerful compared to the entirety of
Western Europe Europe NATO plus EU put
together still more powerful way more
powerful way more powerful than China
and at least twice as powerful as Russia
that's what the US is so
yeah all right let's see what
else
um let us see what else do we
have okay mishmi says just bought your
geopolitical course excited to start but
the course videos are not displayed on
the modu play page I have emailed the
support team okay uh you may have missed
what I said the course becomes live on
the 1st of February right now it is not
live right now it is the pre-order stage
so if you order now you get a discount
that's how it is if you order if you if
you purchase it on the 1st of February
you will have to pay a high you will pay
a higher price so you did you did the
right thing by purchasing it now you got
a discount which was automatically
applied and the course will go live on
the 1 of February that's when you will
get access to the videos and that's when
I will do a an special live stream in
which I will go through the entire
course okay so that is February 1 so
please wait for a few days it's gonna uh
appear live soon soon
enough aush tinglu says VI ramaswami
quits the 2024 presidential race who
according to you is going to
win um maybe Michelle
Obama I'm I'm just
saying uh so it's so look it's clear
that Mr Biden is not going to be the
next nominee for the Democratic party
even though he is the incumbent
president and he has just served one
term so he can run for another ter but
obviously his mental state is not such
that he can take care of himself let
alone run a nation so clearly he's not
going to be I mean if they can
still make him run but it makes no sense
they'll lose that way nobody will vote
for him and nobody will vote for Kamala
Harris so who could it be from the
Democratic party to stand up against
Trump from the Republican side because
it's clear that it will most likely be
Trump who will be the presidential
candidate for the rep
Republicans so who could it be from the
Democratic side who can we think of so I
don't know I'm I'm guessing Michelle
Obama perhaps I mean it's say the US is
a nation of it's an oligarchic Nation
it's a it's a nepotistic
Nation whether you realize it or
not okay so it could be someone like
Michelle Obama or maybe maybe uh who
could it be obviously Arnold schena
can't do it because he was born abroad
not in the US otherwise he would have
loved to run for president Ani I'll be
back uh so who could it be Oprah Winfrey
perhaps uh Dwayne Johnson The Rock could
be some entertainer of some kind just
people will just come and vote for him
or her whoever or it could be Michelle
Obama or or who knows they'll throw
somebody else up but uh from the
Republican side VI has uh predictably
thrown his weight behind Donald
Trump so the thing about viic is this
you know a couple of years ago or
sometime in the past uh I was on the ran
show R ranir alad's podcast and uh I
have done a whole bunch of podcast with
him always fun talking to him great fun
so he asked me about he asked my opinion
about whether Mr Rahul Gandhi could be a
good prime prime ministerial
candidate and I answered him very
honestly I said that I don't know I
don't know because he doesn't have a
track
record a public track record he has
never served as the mayor of a city or
or or the chief minister of a state or
or in any capacity by which would enable
us to judge or gge what capabilities he
has as an administrator as as somebody
who
governs a certain amount of territory or
or that sort of thing we have no idea we
have no
basis by which we can judge his
abilities his strengths his weaknesses
his plus points his negative points his
overall ability there's no way of
judging it similarly when it comes to
viik ramaswami he has no public track
record he has never served in any public
position so he's great at talking he is
tremendously gifted at talking he's
tremendously
articulate and he's always on the point
and and he can demolish any
argument especially when he has the
facts and the truth on his
side so it's like whenever he goes on a
news channel those people are like
scared because he's going to tear them
to Pieces that's how good he is and he
is a self-made billionaire so he's good
at business but he has no public track
record when it comes to governance
all right so it makes sense for somebody
like him who has appeared out of nowhere
and made such a huge impression to now
throw his weight behind the big guy
Trump and endorse Trump and appear with
Trump in all these rallies and all these
events which is going to raise VI's
profile as well and it's going to show
the voter that VI is
loyal is loyal to the boss is loyal to
the big man you see is important so he's
showing his loyalty he's showing his
loyalty to the party to Trump to Maga
and so on and his hope I would say is
that if Donald Trump wins the presidency
then he will get a reasonably good
cabinet position a reasonably high
ranking position hopefully even vice
president even though that may be a
little bit
iffy but he will get some kind of senior
position and then he can build a track
record over the next four years so that
he can then be a serious candidate for
2028 that's VI's deal the way I see it
so who's going to
win uh I somehow get the feeling Trump
won't win because he's an outsider he's
a perenial Outsider in politics you know
where does power come
from excuse me
power is extremely important in politics
and geopolitics and I speak about power
in my in my course there a whole there
are two sections on power but okay let's
come back to this power where does power
come from Power always trumps
money if you watch my old one of my
oldest videos the chingis Khan
video one of the main points in that
video is that power always trumps money
you may have all the money in the world
but but a powerful person can take it
away from you anytime and there's a
difference between power and influence
and power and wealth you may be wealthy
but you may be powerless and so on so
where does what what is it that makes
power that makes somebody powerful it's
networks and
connections and Trump is a very well-
connected and very well networked guy so
why is he powerless in politics because
his Network and his connections are all
in the world of Entrepreneurship and
business and police and so
on okay but not at the top level in
politics so for them he an outsider so
even his party even the elite
politicians in his party see him as an
outsider and then don't they don't like
him that is the thing that is there
against Trump and he wants to clean up
the system well the system won't like it
the system is more powerful than any
individual politician so I get the
feeling it is unlikely that Trump will
win obviously I could be wrong I don't
make predictions but I think on balance
the probability that somebody else will
win from the Democratic side could
possibly be higher so who's going to be
the Democratic candidate if not Biden it
could be Hillary again Hillary Clinton
could come back again perhaps or it
could be a a dark horse a completely
left Feld candidate
Perhaps Perhaps Michelle Obama perhaps
Oprah Winfrey perhaps Dwayne
Johnson or who knows who else somebody
else we'll see we shall
see how do I see Africa in 2024 Africa
is well it's not going to be a place of
great stability we have coup we have
counter CS in Africa the Sahel region
which is known as the C belt has seen a
lot of of all this activity last year
itself we had the coup in N we had the
coup in other Mali as well
um and there's a lot of instability over
here there's a push back against France
there there is Russia getting involved
in the matter the Wagner group is
significantly involved I don't know if
it still exists officially or not
because apparently Mr pan has passed
away in a plane crash and uh so what
shape and form has the Wagner group
taken now obviously they would not just
kill off that group they would not just
end its existence it would still it is
still a powerful potent force of power
projection for Russia and they have a
major presence in Africa so Africa
essentially is the place where the Cold
War 2.0 one of the places where the Cold
War 2.0 is being played out it's a place
where you have proxy wars where you have
proxy coups where you have regime change
attempts and counter attempts and all
that so I think more of more of this
will continue in 2024 I don't see things
will change a lot which is tremendously
sad for the people of Africa because
they once had great culture great
civilization they had their own kingdoms
and Empires and civilizations all of
that was smashed out of existence and
today they are all living in under the
most horrible circumstances some are of
course better off than the others but
some most of Africa is is in is in a
deep poverty and it's all artificially
induced for the purpose of extracting
resources Out of Africa the West has
been the major culprit but now even
China is part of it and the Russians are
just helping
out and looking for their own interests
so I see much of the same continuing in
2024 all right
um what else what
else okay sakam Chan says where do you
see indan GDP in
2035 uh look uh we are in 2024 our GDP
is what 3. something 3.6 3.7 trillion
yes um assuming we grow at 7 six S8
something like that percent per
year uh so how
much so by 25 end 24 end Maybe by mid 25
it could be a $4 trillion doll economy
4.4 4.5 so another by 27 we could be a
$6 trillion do economy and we will will
have leap frogged U Japan and Germany so
that's 6 by 27 and you grow
30 so by
2030 we could be let's say roughly 8
trillion okay roughly 8 trillion by 2035
it could be a $10 trillion economy yeah
I'm just doing some very rough very
basic
uh mental calculations maybe A10
trillion economy by 2035 yeah
uh if we don't get uh embroiled in any
major military conflict or don't do
anything stupid or some or we don't
elect the wrong person to power okay so
that's all up to you my friends make
sure you you vote wisely that's all I
say all right all right all right
um what else do we
have
um all right Tibetan film industry says
say why is the Tibetan cause Tibetan
cause very important for India
well let's take a look at the map as
always so on the map there is no Nation
called Tibet because Tibet is not a
recognized Nation anyway today it is not
a Sovereign Nation anymore the people of
Tibet no longer have
self-determination right they they are
no no longer in control of their own
destiny
they
[Music]
don't so the deal is this historically
Tibet was an independent entity a
sovereign entity it was a sovereign
Kingdom and there was a time in Tibet
about 12 1300 years ago when Tibet was
an extremely milit
militaristically aggressive and Powerful
Nation they cap they captured
at the the then capital of China which
was it Shian was it I forget which city
was the capital of China at the time it
was not Beijing then it was another city
the Tibetans conquered that City and
they installed a puppet Emperor over
there so that's how powerful they were
so Tibet has always been an independent
nation that has separated uh the
sinosphere from the indosphere and Tibet
has always been a part of the indosphere
it was always a part of the overall
civilizational extent of India even
though ethnically linguistically it is
different from India but culturally it
has its own manifestation of Indian
culture so Tibet was part of the
Indian civilizational Zone and Mr Neu
gave that away to China now for the
first time in almost 3,000 years for the
first time since China existed China and
India became neighbors and had a common
border that that's when M this happened
when Mr Neu allowed China to conquer
Tibet by giving tremendous amounts of
rice to the Chinese soldiers who are
starving so for the first time you have
two major Powers India and China that
have a common border and when that
happens there's always going to be
conflict because two nations of such
immense amounts of power and area and
population if they have a common border
there's going to be clashes that is
which is the same reason why the Russia
China border can never be secure can
never be safe and there's always going
to be disputes which is right now
happening the Chinese have raised a new
territorial dispute an old one with
Russia so so therefore for India and
China to be at peace and have friendly
relations like we have always had it is
vital for Tibet to be an independent
nation so that's why that's one that is
the cold hard selfish way of looking at
it why India wants Tibetan
Independence okay that's because it's in
it is in our national interest interest
but on the other side we also have very
ancient cultural and peop to- people
relationships with the people of Tibet
and and we value that and the people of
Tibet are wonderful people and they
deserve their independence and they they
deserve their self their right to
self-determination they deserve for they
deserve their their culture and their
language to keep on existing and not be
be replaced by Chinese culture and
language so the these are the reasons
why Tibet the cause of Tibet is very
important for India and India and China
will be at peace only when Tibet is free
again independent of China again which
probably will take longer than the
reintegration of PO with India but it
will happen
eventually
okay my take on nitish Kumar I have no
take on nitish Kumar I don't talk about
National internal politics I talk about
geopolitics so I don't follow this to I
do follow some of it but uh yeah I I
don't analyze this in great detail and I
I don't talk about it so yeah so if you
want to ask me questions ask me about
geopolitics in history and science if
you like you can ask me about
science all right Joseph P says I think
Andrew Tate red peel manosphere is a
backlash reactionary movement because of
feminism women's rights what is your
opinion on feminism and feminism going
to far well this is a complex topic if
you look at the history of feminism it
goes back to the 19th century and it it
was a legitimate reaction to the status
of women in Western society and feminism
originated in the US okay it originated
in the US and if you look at the way
women were treated in the US in the 19th
century and all women did not have the
right to vote women were essentially
property of men and so on so obviously
there was a need for some kind of
emancipation and some kind of movement
to give women the same dignity and human
rights as
men so that's where feminism originated
and some of
the original pioneers of feminism were
also involved in the civil rights
movement because the African origin
people of the US were treated you know
how horribly they were treated there
were there were segregation laws there
was racism institutionalized racism they
did not have the right to vote they they
did not have the right to enter certain
buildings and so on and so forth so
there was this movement concerted
movement for both causes so the this
this feminist movement originated out of
of something that was really really
necessary okay now what happens in the
1950s and 60s and so on onwards is that
the feminist movement becomes gets
hijacked it gets hijacked by the uh by
by by the by the Marxist movement Neo
Marxist movement so it's not about
bringing Marxism into the us there was a
Marxist takeover ideological takeover
that happened over time of the US
academic system universities colleges
all that if today if you go to the US
universities whichever it is they're
Infested
by socialists and
marxists and that's why the standards in
the US are declining
drastically so the these marxists who
who were all immigres from
Europe they systematically over time
hijacked the feminist movement
also and they they subverted it and then
they used it as another tool
that was used for breaking society and
dividing Society the Marxist framework
is not about equality it's not about uh
emancipation it's not about Dignity of
the pro proletariat it's not about
smashing the Bazi and and uh all that
it's about creating divisions in society
it's a beautiful toolkit it's a great
frame framework beautiful in its
efficacy in efficiency and its its
utility you want to destroy Nation from
within give yourself 50 years yeah it's
a long-term thing 50 maybe 30 years and
then you systematically infil
systematically Infiltrate The Academia
the bureaucracy and various other
decision-making organisms or
organizations in the
country and you replace their their
people with your people and then you
create systematic divisions in the
country so you divide people on the
basis of language you divide people on
the basis of religion you divide people
on the basis of skin color you divide
people on the basis of imagined
oppression which happened hundreds of
years ago you divide people on the basis
of of gender you divide people on the
basis of of sexuality these days today
there are like 782 different sexualities
or genders of God knows what so you
create further and further and further
and further divisions in society so you
and this is done by by taking one group
of people and telling them you have been
oppressed and then taking another group
of people and saying that these are your
oppressors the they have oppressed you
and then you make them fight and then
you do this over and over
again so the so today what you have
feminism is mored into this sort of
thing which is essentially about
victimizing men blaming men for
everything that is wrong with Society I
mean we are the same species men and
women are part of the same thing we are
not different species but anyway I'll
not go into the arguments and
counterarguments and all that but that's
what it is about so it's gone too far
it's become a divisive force in society
feminism obviously was was it it it
originated out of a genuine need to
emancipate women for the from the
horrors of Western
society and now it's it's gone the other
way around now it's about oppressing men
and about blaming men for everything and
so on so obviously there's going to be a
backlash when there's a reaction there's
a counter reaction in society and
everywhere else and that's where you
have it that's where you have it all
right all right right
right okay once again the same question
some media houses claim that France
plans to share aircraft engine
technology with India do you think it
will actually happen I think the talks
will go on for rounds and rounds and
rounds and and go into very specific
speciic tiny details about which thing
can be shared which cannot be shared and
what can be done what cannot be done and
so on so forth I think it's it's going
to be a long drone out extended process
and overall I like the French but
overall I am not overall very very
hopeful about this so India should not F
its jet engine development program keep
it going and if possible acquire
something from the French and then you
do the best of whatever you have so I am
not extremely optimistic about this but
I am not zero in my optimism so I'm
cautiously cautiously slightly less
optimistic but I'm still optimistic
that's what I would say all
right
okay let us um take some more questions
lots of
questions
um okay RI Singh says please do tell us
about India's cyber capabilities are we
working on it behind the curtains or do
we not have any hold on it listen if you
look at government Communications press
releases all that there is no mention of
India cyber
capabilities there is
no cyber warfare cyber capabilities of
India Etc are never mentioned anywhere
in any press release in any government
communication in the news anything at
all it's never mentioned
anywhere so I am not previe to any
confidential information okay all I see
is what's in the public
domain the data that you have access to
that's the data that I have access to it
depends on how well you can analyze the
data so what I can say is that I have no
extra information compared to you about
India cyber
capabilities but the fact that we don't
talk about it I think that is a very
encouraging thing for
me I think India has reasonably good
cyber capabilities now
now I think it is opinion it is not
based on facts it's based on logic and
inference but it's like um it's like a
neural network you can't really explain
how you how the neural network came up
with this calculation and this output
but it did this calculation so it's like
that so I believe that India has pretty
strong cber capabilities now but I don't
really have any data to back me up when
I make this claim so you can take it
with a grain of salt if you like
all
right uh what was
this okay comments are coming in really
fast okay Dr Pera 5 2556 says if China
becomes superpower what's going to
happen to the South China SE China is
not going to be a superpower let me tell
you why okay I don't have the thing on
the screen right now if you compare see
people think of two Nations when the
term superpower comes to mind Indians
always think about India as well but
let's be realistic right now okay let's
be
realistic if you look at the
overall power of the us whether it is
their very basic things like area and
population if we talk about their
economic
strength the American economic strength
is close to double there of China not
double let's say 1.5 times there of
China so they are kind of neck and neck
when it comes to economic strength the
US is not leagues ahead of China it's
about 1.5 times of China when it comes
to military strength the US is like
three times as powerful as China
militarily right when it comes to
nuclear strength the US leaves China in
the
dust way behind the US is an immense
nuclear Arsenal second only to Russia
China is nowhere near anywhere near the
US in terms of nuclear strength when it
comes to power
projection China can't even begin
comparing itself with the US when it
comes to power projection power
projection means the amount of power you
can project extra
territorially the US is Lees ahead of
any nearest peer
competitor there's no comparison so if
you take all of this together and if you
take into consideration energy
self-sufficiency also which is very
important then you will see the US is
roughly 10 times or let's say eight
times as powerful as China China is not
even
close it's not even half of the us it's
about
1/8 of the
US roughly roughly okay so China is
nowhere close to being anywhere near
being a super I don't know what I'm
saying but you know you get what I mean
I mean look at the map and I'll tell you
I mean it should be obvious when we just
take a look at the map China wants what
China wants Taiwan where is Taiwan where
is Taiwan right next to Taiwan right
next to China then why can't China take
back Taiwan even though it's in its own
backyard because the US is too powerful
for China even
here okay so China is nowhere near being
a superpower and with the kind of
demographic decline it is seeing it's
never going to happen
China is never going to be a
superpower and if you if you were to
compare China and the US I would say
that us is about eight times as powerful
as China if you were to compare India
and
China China is about three and a half
times as powerful as India overall so
this is
just hard facts all right so yeah so
China is not going to be a superpower
that's that's the actual answer that's
the actual answer it's not going to be a
superpower all the hype don't don't
believe the hype that media gives you
and so-called so-called
experts speak about China superpower no
China is not a
superpower uh yeah see I just answered
the question China isn't half of the US
China is about 1/8 of the US roughly
speaking and India is roughly onethird
of
China so that tells you to be a
superpower is going to be a long long
long process India should forget about
these wonderful terminologies these
wonderful terms super power visha Guru
focus on the very
Basics focus on taking one step in front
of the other not look at how high the
mountain is just focus on the next step
and keep taking the next step and the
next step and the next step and don't
think too far India is nowhere close to
being a superpower China itself is
nowhere close to being a superpower
nowhere near all right so India isn't
going to be be a superpower in by 2050
no way impossible but India is already
great power India will surpass China by
2050 yeah India will probably surpass
China by 2050 India will most likely be
number two by 2050 it is very much
possible so that's the next Target we
should talk about not about these status
symbols like superp power and Vish Guru
forget about status
we should pursue actual hard power hard
power that can be measured in numbers
numbers are everything thoughts and
emotions and feelings and and status is
nothing you should we should Pur pursue
hard growth numerical growth numerical
figures that's all that we need to look
at we have to be
realistic all
right I already I already spoke about uh
the Texas border so
um
aush says we do you do you think that
mosad Israel knew about the Hamas attack
but decided to do nothing about it so as
to use it an excuse to end Hamas once
and for all it's kind of a crazy Theory
well it's it's kind of hard to believe
that the the Israelis knew nothing about
this would what was going to happen
apparently the Egyptians had tipped off
the the Israelis that something big is
going to happen and it's going to happen
pretty soon and the the Israelis have
tremendous amounts of surveillance
capabilities and electronic surveillance
signals surveillance human intelligence
and God knows what it's I mean it's hard
to believe that they did not know this
is going to happen and the reaction time
was so slow even after the the thing is
set in motion the the border fencing is
cut I mean they had sensors there they
had motion detectors how come they did
not react in time these slow moving
paragliders come in I mean how did they
not react to that on time in time so
yeah it looks kind of weird but I don't
have any actual answers because uh who
knows what really happened and why it
happened but yeah what you are saying is
not a crazy Theory it kind of is a very
legitimate question that needs to be
asked all
right um let us see what else we have
critical Akil says what is critical
thinking how can we start thinking
critically uh also please explain what's
the meaning of first principles thinking
critical thinking means you look see we
humans are a
combination of uh logic and emotion
there's a logical side to our our
thinking thinking process logic and
there's an emotional side to our
thinking process where everything is
clouded by whatever emotion we are
currently going through that's why
people need motivational speeches when
you listen to motivational speech with
by nice epic music and all that you feel
all motivated yeah let me go and do this
but that's just the
emotion after a while after 10 minutes
15 minutes half an hour the emotion will
go back to Baseline and then what
happens then how do you progress when
the emotion emotional hit is gone so
critical thinking is about setting your
emotions aside all right and just
thinking calmly and logically
logic so that is critical thinking look
at both sides of the coin when there is
an issue when there's a problem to be
solved you look at it from all angles
how can I best solve the problem I don't
care whether the cat is black or white
as long as it catches mice that's
critical thinking so critical thinking
is about thinking logically and
rationally and coldly and
unemotionally and using logic and
calculation as far as possible use
mathematical calculations and numbers
that's critical thinking and if you
can't do that you have to make
assumptions but smart assumptions
probabilistic
assumptions and and use hard logic so in
science in physics many of the things
that we talk about don't have exact
answers what is the probability that UA
mua
was an alien
artifact so if you ask me was umu mua an
alien artifact I would say I don't know
but if you ask me what's the probability
then I could actually give you
probabilistic figures based on actual
logical calculations
based on the properties of the object
and so on so that is critical thinking
if you ask me do aliens exist I'll say
what the hell how do we know have we
seen any aliens no we have not seen if
you ask me what is the probability that
aliens exist or don't exist then I can
give you actual facts and figures so
it's all about probabilistic thinking
when you don't have hard figures and and
logical thinking that's critical
thinking what is the meaning of first
principles thinking you ask why 78 times
not 78 times maybe five
times okay that's what it do there's a
question
why is the sky
blue then how do we answer the
question right so then you ask the
question what is the actual color of the
sun then you'll say it's yellow but I'll
then ask you then what's the question
what's the color of the sun when you go
outside the atmosphere into space so my
point is you go back you peel back the
layer step by step by step until you go
back to the very first principles the
first principles in any field is the
basics
so when you talk about question of the
sky being blue and all you have to go
back to the first principles of physics
which is quantum mechanics in this case
Railway scattering and all that forget
about that but when it comes to
geopolitics and all we have to go back
to the very basic fundamentals of what
is power what is energy what is force
what is the national interest break it
down to the very Basics and then use
only those Basics to examine the entire
world that is first principles
thinking not abstract thinking but
complete basic first principles which
cannot be broken down
further that is that is first principles
thinking it's about asking why why why I
ask why you get an answer then you ask
why is that the answer then you go back
one layer deeper and then you get
another answer you you ask why is that
the answer you go back one level deeper
you go back deeper and deeper and deeper
until there is no more dep to reach
because you've gone back to the very
fundamentals gone down to the very
fundamentals so it's all but
fundamentals of any and the basic
principles of any field that is first
principles thinking so that's what it is
all right I think we have gone past 2
hours 11 minutes so I think that should
be the end of today's session wonderful
session thank you so much for all the
questions once again uh let me remind
you I have launched the geopolitics
course and
uh yes I have launched the geopolitics
course the link is in the chat let let
me once again put it up here we have it
so it's it's called geopolitics from
first
principles I get this question all the
time is there any book any course that
you can refer to to learn geopolitics so
this is it there is no book that's
available that I know of that teaches
you
geopolitics the fundamentals of
geopolitics but this course is going to
do exactly that it's going to break it
down to the basics and it's going to
give you the ability to actually
calculate the power of a Nation compare
Nations and compare the strength and
weaknesses precisely of Nations it's
going to put you in the top 5% of
geopolitical analysts if you take this
course so if you are serious about
learning geopolitics go ahead and take
this course it's going to launch on the
1st of February but it's available for
pre-ordering right now if you order
before the 1st of February you will get
a discount so if you're interested
please go ahead ahead and purchase the
course and thank you so much for
watching I really appreciate all the
questions and we're going to do a lot
more live streams this year ask abijit
and we're going to have a lot more other
content as well on this channel this
year so thank you so much I wish you all
a good day great day good night wherever
you are and I'll see you very soon in
the next video and the next live stream
thank you so much and I'll see you next
time